<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An historicall and true discourse, of a voyage made by the Admirall Cornelis Matelife the yonger, into the East Indies, who departed out of Holland, in May 1605 With the besieging of Malacca, and the battaile by him fought at sea against the Portugales in the Indies, with other discourses. Translated out of the Dutch, according to the coppie printed at Rotterdam.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119993</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855197</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855197</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20675</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20675)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 721:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An historicall and true discourse, of a voyage made by the Admirall Cornelis Matelife the yonger, into the East Indies, who departed out of Holland, in May 1605 With the besieging of Malacca, and the battaile by him fought at sea against the Portugales in the Indies, with other discourses. Translated out of the Dutch, according to the coppie printed at Rotterdam.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By G. Eld] for William Barret, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard; at the signe of the greene Dragon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Matelief, Cornelis, 1569-1632.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20675:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20675:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Hiſtoricall and true diſcourſe, of a voyage made by the <hi>Admirall</hi> Cornelis Matelife <hi>the</hi> yonger, into the Eaſt Indies, who departed <hi>out of Holland, in May</hi> 1605. With the beſieging of <hi>Malacca,</hi> and the battaile by him fought at Sea againſt the <hi>Portugales in the Indies, with other diſcourſes.</hi> Tranſlated out of the Dutch, according to the coppie printed at <hi>Rotterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of William Barret, featuring a gilly-flower (McKerrow 320)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>William Barret,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules Church-yard, at the ſigne of the greene Dragon, 1608.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:20675:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20675:2"/>
            <head>An hiſtoricall and true diſcourſe of a voyage made by the Admirall <hi>Cornelis Matelief the younger, into the Eaſt Indies, who departed out of Holland in May, Anno.</hi> 1605.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N regard that wee began our voyage ſome-what too late in the yeare, it fell out to be ſo much the longer, (as I wrote vnto your worſhips in Ianuary laſt, from the Iland <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritio,</hi> by the Admirall <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vander Haghen:</hi>) from whence we departed the 27. of Ianuary, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the paſſage of thoſe ſhallow places, wee cauſed our Pinnaſſes or ſmall boates to ſayle before, and in the night time to hang out Lanthornes, by which meanes wee got ouer the flats of <hi>Nazare,</hi> ouer the North point called <hi>Haya de Malſa,</hi> and <hi>Perodes Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hos,</hi> and made toward <hi>Chagros,</hi> but could not get the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the North, and therefore tooke our courſe Southerly, and found no ground: from thence wee paſt betweene <hi>Pulo Malueo,</hi> and the <hi>Maldiues,</hi> but ſaw no land vntill the two and twenty of March, yet wee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20675:3"/>eſpied the Iland of <hi>Sumatra,</hi> which is the point of <hi>Achin,</hi> but could not reach it.</p>
            <p>The 28. of Ianuary wee drew neere to the <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bares,</hi> where wee tooke in freſh water, and got ſome <hi>Coques</hi> Nuttes, and a few Hennes, in which place the inhabitants goe altogether naked: there I thought to haue gotten ſome Amber, which if I had ſtayed there, I might haue got for fiue blankes. There our men went on ſhoare, and hauing muſtered, prepared ſome inſtruments of wood which I as then wanted.</p>
            <p>At which time our ſouldiers and Sailers, deſiring to know to what parts they were bound (for that as then they began to murmure amongſt them-ſelues, ſaying, that they were not hyred to fight on land (and ſome of the chiefeſt Sailers ſtoutly maintained it.) I ſhewed them that the ſtates commiſſaries Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion giuen vnto me, was to beſiege and win the towne of <hi>Malacca,</hi> ſetting before their eyes what honor and great profit they were to expect from thence, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſmall perill which they had to incurre: ſaying, that I would ſend them to no other place, but where I would hazard mine owne life with them, promiſing them that if they chanced to winne the towne by force of aſſault, they ſhould haue the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacking thereof, and if that they got it by treatie and compoſition, they ſhould likewiſe haue that they found therein, reſeruing ſome part thereof to fortifie the towne withall, wherewith they were much incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, and reſolutely with one voyce, cryed out and ſayd, that they were fully reſolued to win the towne,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20675:3"/>and with that reſolution wee ſayled through the Straights: and vpon the laſt of Aprill, arriued within halfe a mile of <hi>Malacca,</hi> with the loſſe of two men onely, that dyed by the way.</p>
            <p>And being come before <hi>Malacca,</hi> I commanded that foure ſhips that lay in the road, (whereof one was laden for <hi>China,</hi>) ſhould bee ſet on fire, but my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion being not obſerued, my men giuing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to drinking, they let them make away, where they had three men ſlaine, and fifteene wounded: but I willed them onely to burne them, and not to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them.</p>
            <p>The next day after we conſulted about our landing (for that order had beene taken long before how wee ſhould land, and what euery man ſhould doe) ſome were of opinion to land preſently, others ſaid that it was not expedient for vs to land ſo haſtily in a ſtrange countrey, not knowing the enemies forces, and that it was beſt for vs to ſtay the comming of the King of <hi>Ihor</hi> that was looked for within eight or ten dayes, for wee perceiued a wood neere vnto the ſhore, much to the enemies aduantage to play vpon vs from thence, we not being able to purſue them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alledged that they thought it not good to put the whole Fleete in danger, before the comming of the King of <hi>Ihor:</hi> who being arriued with two or three thouſand men, they ſayd wee might land boldly, and put our enemy in great feare: this was the iudgment of the greater part of vs, which did preuaile, though I my ſelfe liked better of our preſent landing.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20675:4"/>
            <p>The eight of May we landed with the King of <hi>Ihor,</hi> (who had about three thouſand men with him,) and in our landing loſt not one man; for the <hi>Portugales</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two or three hundred, that ſtood ready on the ſhore to reſiſt vs, ſuddenly retired into the ſuburbes of the towne, where they defended themſelues till mid night, and then ſetting them on fire, and breaking the bridge, ranne into the towne. In my aduiſe ſent vnto the Commiſſaries, I haue declared what I haue done before <hi>Malacca,</hi> vntill the eight of Auguſt, and what ſmall ayde and aſſiſtance we haue receiued from the <hi>Ihorites,</hi> with the diſorder and mutiny of our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the ſtrength of the towne, their ſallies out againſt vs, and how they haue with credit beene driuen back againe by vs, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>At ſuch time as we intended to remooue our ſiege, in regarde that the Portingales <hi>Armado</hi> as then laye hard by <hi>Capo Rachado,</hi> which is about twelue miles from <hi>Malacca:</hi> they of <hi>Malacca</hi> thought verily eyther to ſpoile vs, or to hinder our pretence (they of <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyc</hi> being all gone aboorde, except a hundred and twenty, or a hunderd and thirty men,) and iſſuing out of the towne with all the men they could make, ſet vpon vs, but we couragiouſly draue them back againe, with the loſſe of fifty of their men, and but one man of ours hurt.</p>
            <p>This done, for the ſpace of two nights I was much troubled about ſhipping of our Ordnance, in regarde that the ſtreame was not ſwift, whereby the water could not get to the ſhore, &amp; the ground very muddy,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20675:4"/>ſo that I could hardly get our Canon aboord, but God prouided ſo well for vs, that vpon the 16. day we all got aboord, and left not any thing on the ſhoare, hauing about three hundred hurt and ſicke men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. Notwithſtanding the 17. of Auguſt we ſet forward to encounter our enimy, whoſe Fleete was 14. Galions, 4. Galleys, and 15. or 16. Fuſtes or Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, and two or three Galions, came two or three dayes after vnto their Fleete: that euening we ſhotte againſt them, and chaſed them, but in the night they put on more ſailes, and wee following after them all the next day, holding our courſe Northerly. The next night following I layd mee downe to ſleepe, for I had taken no reſt in three dayes and three nights before, beeing much buſied about our Ordinance: In the meane time <hi>Dyrick Mol</hi> maiſter of my ſhip came vnto me, ſhewing me that the enemy out-ſailed vs, asking me whether wee ſhould put on any more ſailes, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, yea; and willed him at any hand to keepe them ſtill in fight. Not long after that he came againe, and tolde mee that the enemy had caſt Anchor, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon I charged him to Anchor alſo, and to keepe aboue the winde: The reſt of our ſhips anchred loofe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, a Canon ſhot wide from the enemy. In the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before the breake of day, I cauſed a peece to bee ſhotte off, to warne to ſet ſaile, for as then the enemy had gotten ſome-what more, and had the loofe of vs: and at the ſame time alſo ſhotte off a warning peece vnto his ſhippe. Our ſhippe called the <hi>Naſſau,</hi> was long winding vp of her Anchor; and before I could
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20675:5"/>make ſignes vnto her to cut the cable, a <hi>Portugall</hi> ſhip aborded her, which I perceiuing, wound my ſhippe about to ayde her, but the Sea was ſo calme, that I could not reache her, but by force borded <hi>Simon Man,</hi> and could by no meanes get from him. The Admirall <hi>Alioza de Caruailla,</hi> ſeeing vs faſt together, boorded <hi>Symon Mau,</hi> and <hi>Henrico de Loroinge</hi> boorded mee, (theſe two were the greateſt Gallions the enemy had): after that came <hi>Duarte de Guerra,</hi> and fell alſo vpon mee, where-with wee gaue fire on all ſides, at which encounter moſt part of <hi>Duarte de Guerras</hi> men were kild, and hee himſelfe alſo: <hi>Alioza de Caruailla</hi> forſooke his ſhip, and was likewiſe ſlaine: <hi>Don Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co</hi> receiued more then a hundred ſhottes thorough his ſhip.</p>
            <p>Afterwards <hi>Claes Gherritſz</hi> Maiſter of the <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> fell vpon <hi>Duarte de Guerra,</hi> and ſet her on fire, whereby our blind alſo was ſet on fire: the other <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall</hi> ſhips would haue ſet vpon vs, but durſt not for the fire, meane time I caſt out an Anchor which was cut off by my men, but they ſayd that it was done by the fire. The <hi>Mauritius</hi> looſed himſelfe, &amp; <hi>Simon Man</hi> of <hi>Middleborough</hi> draue from vs, with <hi>Duarte de Guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> and <hi>Alioza de Caruailla,</hi> but the people for the moſt part were all ſlaine, I hauing caſt out another Anchor, called vnto them to caſt one of their Cables vnto vs to ſtay them, but the noyſe was ſo great that they heard vs not, ſo that they burnt all together. <hi>Simon Mau</hi> ſaued the moſt part of his men, except eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene that were hurt, and ſome that were taken
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20675:5"/>priſoners, that were afterwards releaſed by my meanes. I was ſtill faſt grapled to <hi>Henrico,</hi> to whom I promiſd his life if hee would yeeld, (for hee could not defend himſelfe, which hee promiſed to doe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his men being very deſirous to come ouer into our ſhip, but I refuſed them (yet twelue of them came aboord) fearing that my men would fall to the ſpoile, for they had twiſe more men then wee, and our anchor would not hold, and ſtill the enemyes fleete approached, wee beeing very weary, my Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and my Captaine beeing ſlaine, and the chiefe Marchant hurt, whereof not long after hee dyed, and I was forced to bee preſent at euery conflict. Whervpon I commanded <hi>Don Henrico</hi> to caſt out an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, but hee excuſed himſelfe, ſaying, that hee was not able to doe it, for which cauſe I ſent a man to looke whether it were ſo or not, which gaue himſelfe to the ſpoyle; then I ſent an other that tooke the maiſters Whiſtle from his necke, but comming back againe, ſayd that the ſhippe was full of dead men, and that the anchors were loſt, and the cables ſhotte in peeces, by the Canon ſhotte. Where-vpon I cauſed a Rope to bee brought out at the Sterne, to faſten it vnto vs. In the meane time our anchor tooke holde, and his ſhip brake from vs, and ſo I loſt my prize: which ſhewes that they which make many delayes, are often diſappointed, ſo that it ſeemes that marſhall affaires muſt bee vndertaken with quick and ſpeedy reſolution. This grieued vs much, but there was no remedie: This happened about euening.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20675:6"/>
            <p>One of the enemies ſhips alſo boorded the <hi>Naſſau,</hi> at which time alſo their Vice-roy fell vpon him on the other ſide, but could not winne him, and therefore ſet the Gallery, and the Sterne of her on fire, and ſo ſhee was burnt, the Vice-roy likewiſe had been burnt with her if the Galleyes had not pluckt him away by force.</p>
            <p>The moſt part of the <hi>Naſſaus</hi> men were ſaued: <hi>Mauritius</hi> and the <hi>Black Lion</hi> thought to haue falne vpon the Viceroy; but the winde was too calme, the reſt of our ſhips did their endeuours, but there were ſome faint-hearted amongſt them, notwithſtanding wee held out, and fought all that day, although vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately with loſſe of two ſhips on either ſide.</p>
            <p>The next day being the nineteene of Auguſt, all our ſhips being repayred, wee reſolued to recouer our loſſes, for the which wee were much grieued, but if the <hi>Naſſau</hi> had cut her Anchors in time, wee had not boorded one the other, and it had fallen out better for vs.</p>
            <p>The twentieth of Auguſt wee fell to it againe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I found not my men ſo ready and reſolute as before, for thoſe that had eſcaped out of the ſhippes that were burnt, eſpecially they of <hi>Middleborough,</hi> asked mee where they ſhould haue their moneths pay, wherevnto I anſwered, that it was then no time to ſpeake of ſuch matters; and that I knew not how the Commiſſaries would vnderſtand theſe things, and yet I ſayd I was informed that they had beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued themſelues valiantly, and that therefore it was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20675:6"/>no reaſon but that they ſhould haue their due, and that to my power I would defend and maintaine them in all iuſt cauſes. Within an houre after, the men of my ſhip alſo came vnto mee, and demanded ſecurity for their moneths pay; or elſe they ſaid they would not fight: they had ſome ſetters on, which as yet I dare not name. This made mee halfe abaſht, yet I vſed all the meanes that I could poſſible to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe them, and at the laſt they ſeemed to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented.</p>
            <p>About the euening wee approched the enemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and then I firſt obſerued what danger the words (of reſpectiue ſhips) ſet downe in our Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles brought vs into: for by meanes of the loſſe of the two ſhippes aforeſaid, euery one drew back from ioyning with the enemy, beeing lothe to vſe his hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poteke or aſſurance, whereby wee were not halfe ſo forward to ſet vpon our enemy as wee were at the firſt; for not ſo much as a Swabber in the ſhippe but hee would diſpute vpon the wordes of Reſpectiue ſhips, for whereas it is ſayd, that for the aſſurance of their pay, they ſhall haue the ſhip wherein they ſerued, and the goods that were in it and no more, euery one was carefull for his owne.</p>
            <p>That day and the next wee ſhotte diuers times at the Viceroy, but I perceiuing that wee had not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der enough to ouer-come ſuch an army, nor bullets to ſerue our turnes, though I had cauſed ſome to bee made before <hi>Malacca;</hi> but not ſufficient, wee left off.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20675:7"/>
            <p>The ſhipps that ſtayde behinde came neere vnto the enemy, that had his rowing Pinnaſſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee could fetch water when hee would, and in our ſight carryed his hurt men to <hi>Malacca,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon wee called a counſell together, and reſolued to goe to <hi>Ihor,</hi> chiefly to releaſe our ſhips, for it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that our enemy could ſayle better then wee, as alſo to refreſh out ſicke men, to make Bullets, and to incourage the King: this wee performed at <hi>Ihor,</hi> which hath one of the beſt riuers of the world: there wee made Bullets, but could get but little refreſhing for money, I alſo incouraged the King of <hi>Ihor,</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling him to fortifie his towne, and ſhewed him how hee ſhould doe it, which at laſt was begunne, and had ſoone beene finiſhed, if the Hollanders would haue wrought.</p>
            <p>Wee departed thence the thirteene of October, and the twentith came before <hi>Malacca,</hi> and for the ſpace of ſixe dayes laye in ſight of the Towne, but could not approach neere vnto it by reaſon of the winde, ſo that the enemy placed all his ſhipps, being ſeauen Galeons and three Galleys (for the fourth was ſhotte to peeces by <hi>Capo Rachado</hi>) in a rowe, and all his Canon on the one ſide. Wee there-vpon taking counſell reſolued to ſet vpon the enemy, but becauſe wee had little prouiſion of pouder, and a long iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to make home-ward, and perceiuing that wee could not ſeperate their ſhippes with ſhooting, wee agreed that three of our ſhips ſhould boord them, which I thought to haue done in the night time,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20675:7"/>taking with mee the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and the <hi>Froninee</hi> of <hi>Delſe,</hi> but could not by reaſon of the ſtreame: the morning beeing coole and cleere, and fitte to take ſome-thing in hand, the winde comming from the land, and wee lying Northerly from the roade, wee made ſaile, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to fall vpon their ſhippe that lay moſt Southerly and moſt beneath the ſtreame, for the water began to turne, but the winde was ſo ſharpe, that I could ſcant paſſe by the roade, ſo that wee approached neere to <hi>Illa das noas,</hi> and woond about it, but could not ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any of them, but vpon that which laye Norther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt (which was the greateſt Gallion next vnto the Vice-royes, and had in her nineteene Braſſe peeces, and three Yron peeces, a hundred and three ſcore <hi>Portingales,</hi> and as many <hi>Moores</hi> (I willed my maiſter called <hi>Symon Lambrechtſz Man,</hi> whom I had taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſhip, in the ſteed of <hi>Dirick Mol</hi> that was ſlaine, to ſet vpon her. Wee were forced to paſſe by all the ſhippes of the enemy, not without ſome hurt vnto vs, but I ſhotte not at all, reſcuing euery thing ready vntill our aboording, but when wee were halfe way forward amongſt the enemies ſhips, my Maiſter and the Pylote counſelled mee to turne our courſe, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I made anſwer, that I wanted no aduiſe nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, to delay them of till wee were aboord the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and ſo held on vntill we boorded her, and ſo let a Dragge fall, appointing ten Muſquetters to keepe it, and to hinder that the enemy ſhould not looſe it, which the enemy ſought to doe: I willed them alſo to ſhoote continually towards their <hi>Merſch,</hi> and from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20675:8"/>our Merſch and garnates, I cauſed ſtones and fire-balles to bee caſt, whereby the enimie was driuen vnder his net. And as ſoone as I had faſtned vppon him, the <hi>Sunne</hi> fell on his other ſide, and the <hi>Prouince</hi> came behinde vs, and brake his Spritt againſt the enemies ſhippes, the Galion had an anchor before the flood, and a cable faſtned at the Vice-royes ſhip, but the cable was preſently cutte in peeces, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the cable that faſtened the Viceroy vnto him, and ſo wee draue together towards the Lee: the other <hi>Portugales</hi> perceiuing that, hoyſed their ſailes (which was that which I aymed at, to drawe them from the wall,) and made to ſea-ward. Wee fell vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Saint <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and killed all the men, except eight <hi>Portingalles,</hi> that hidde them-ſelues vnder the Ballaſt, and ſo wee tooke her.</p>
            <p>My Maiſter and the Pilote ſayd, that it was not expedient that two of our ſhippes ſhould be bound to one ſhippe, and that wee ſhould leaue the <hi>Sunne</hi> alone with it, and fall vpon the Viceroy that drew neere vnto vs, which counſell I liked not, fearing to haue the like chance that I had with <hi>Henrico.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A little while after <hi>Roobol</hi> Maiſter of the great <hi>Sunne,</hi> called vnto mee, to pray mee to let him alone in the ſhippe, and that hee would carry it to the Sea, which I would not conſent vnto, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that I could not doe any thing to my minde, I leaft it: and preſently the weather was very calme, the <hi>Portingales</hi> ſhippes laye loofe-ward from vs, whereof one made towards the great <hi>Sunne,</hi> but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20675:8"/>hee could not, fearing to be clapt on boord by vs, we perceiuing that the calme either hindred vs to come togither; I ſent a boate to <hi>Roobol</hi> willing him to ſet fire in the ſhippe, where vnto hee anſwered that I ſhould hold my peace, and ſayd hee would not do it, in the meane time hee got him-ſelfe looſe, by what meanes I know not, and hoyſing vp his great ſayle, ranne more then a myle from the Fleete not once looking backe: In the meane while two Portingale ſhippes boorded the Vize-admirall, againſt whome came <hi>Mauritius</hi> and the Blacke Lion, and behaued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo well, that the one of th'enemies ſhippes was burnt, and the other ſpoyled. The <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſet vppon a portingale, but they were preſently ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated againe, and I ſayling by him willed him to bord him againe, which he did, but they were preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeperated againe. The great calme hindred mee that I could not come neere them: after that a whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde ryſing, ſcattered the ſhippes; and with that <hi>Mauritius</hi> made towards the Portingale againe, <hi>Eraſmus</hi> and I alſo turning towards him, which the Portingale perceiuing, yeelded vnto vs, where wee killed foure and forty Portingales, and tooke out of her eight peeces of braſſe, and ſo ſet fire on hir. In the ſhippe which the Vize-admirall burnt there was not ſo much as a catte or a dogge ſaued: The ſhippe that <hi>Roobol</hi> did let go, was driuen by the Gallies to the ſhoare, and ſo the euening came vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs.</p>
            <p>The next morning, the Vizeroys ſhippe lying
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20675:9"/>formoſt, I made towards him, but my Maiſter and Pilot tolde mee that I could not reach him; for which cauſe I made to the Galion Saint <hi>Symon,</hi> that yeelded it ſelfe vnto mee, for the men were moſt of them runne from him: the Captaine with twenty men onely remaining in her: out of her I tooke foureteene peeces, ſome fleſh, wine, and pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſo ſet it on fire.</p>
            <p>This (thankes bee vnto GOD) was the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of our battaile, without any great loſſe of men, wee burnt three Gallions, wherein many Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen were ſlaine, and aboue foure hundred <hi>Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale</hi> ſouldiers, as I was after informed by certaine intercepted letters; wee our ſelues made our vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory bloudy, for our men were ſo diuiliſhly giuen ſo ſeeke after prey and bootie, that rowing round about the Gallion that burnt, they fell to ranſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the men that ſwum in the water, whereby the fire got into the powder, and burnt three of our boates, wherein wee loſt foure and twenty men of the <hi>White Lyon,</hi> eighteene of the <hi>Black Lion,</hi> eleuen of the <hi>Vice-Admirall,</hi> ſeauen of the <hi>Prouince,</hi> and fiue of the great <hi>Sunne.</hi> God forgiue them their ouer-ſight.</p>
            <p>The eight and twentie day wee went againe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Malacca;</hi> intending to burne the <hi>Vice-roy</hi> and the <hi>Paule,</hi> but as wee had concluded the euening before to performe it: the next morning the <hi>Vice-roy</hi> himſelfe cauſed fire to bee put into three of the Gallions, ſo great was their feare: I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20675:9"/>ſeeing that preſently retired, thinking them to bee fire ſhippes ſent for to burne vs.</p>
            <p>After that I made agreement to releaſe the Portingales, that were in all a hundred ſeauenty fiue, and as many Moores, vppon condition that the Viceroy ſhould ſend mee all my Duch-men that were priſoners in <hi>Mallacca,</hi> and that hee had in any place within the <hi>Indies;</hi> and that three Captaines, <hi>Christianus Swarez, Andreas Peſo,</hi> and <hi>Ferdinando Marcado,</hi> ſhould pay fiue thouſand Ducats for their ranſome, which ſhould bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided amongſt our men.</p>
            <p>Which accordingly was performed, beſide a thouſand Ducats which are not yet payd, for two Portingales, whereof one left his brother with me in hoſtage: This money I deuided amongſt the Saylers, euery one hauing fiue ryals of eight, (for the Ducats make but ſixe ryals) to make them the willinger to ſette vppon the reſt of the Armado that was gone to <hi>Niſobaer.</hi> The chiefe thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the noting was that when I came the ſecond time within the ſight of <hi>Mallacca,</hi> there roſe a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie in ſome of the ſhips ſaying that they would not fight, and alledging that they entred not into ſeruice to that end, ſaying that it was true that they had made me a promiſe to make a triall vpon <hi>Niſobaer</hi> but that they ſaid was performed before <hi>Mallacca:</hi> and alſo at <hi>Capo Rachado,</hi> as they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed: the moſt part of them yeelded to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but thoſe of the Vice-Admirall ſaid they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20675:10"/>would giue eare to nothing, ſo that I was forced to vſe ſome threatning wordes, and ſayd that for all their deniall the matter ſhould not goe as they would haue it, and ſo willing, nilling, they went on with the reſt.</p>
            <p>Thus I went with all the ſhippes to <hi>Niſobaer,</hi> though I intended to haue ſent the <hi>White-Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Vice-admirall</hi> toward; <hi>Bantham,</hi> there to take in their lading, and the next yeare to bee at home: but the moſt voyces would haue vs all to goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to <hi>Niſobaer,</hi> and to trie whether wee could ſeperat their ſhippes, which wee hoped to finde all diſperſed, as alſo to get the King of <hi>Queda</hi> on our ſide, to the end that no victuals ſhould bee carried from thence to <hi>Malacca,</hi> and ſo wee came before <hi>Queda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The nineteene of Nouember I offered my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice vnto the King, ſhowing him that I was come thether to helpe him for to driue the <hi>Portingales</hi> out of his dominions, and to chaſe them from his Hauen, according to his letters written vnto mee, and ſent to <hi>Bataſaner,</hi> and that I was deſirous to lade a ſhippe there, becauſe his name was not yet knowne in our countrey, which I ſayd would tend vnto his honor and profit. The King glad to heare that, prayed mee to helpe him to take a <hi>Pourtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale</hi> ſhippe and two Fregattes that laye in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: Where-vpon I preſently ſent three Boates that the ſame night ſet thoſe three ſhippes on fire, after that the <hi>Maleyes</hi> had taken the goods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20675:10"/>out of them, for I charged my men to take nothing from thence, there I tooke a praw com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from <hi>Malacca,</hi> and therein ſome letters, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining that their <hi>Armado</hi> was not farre from <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo Bouton,</hi> and meant to ſayle to the <hi>Indies</hi> the fourth of December: therfore I made haſt to follow them, before that the foure Fregattes with a hundred and foure and twentie men and munition of warre, ſhould come vnto them, and ioyne with them.</p>
            <p>The ninth of December wee gotte to <hi>Paulo Bouton,</hi> and ſaw the <hi>Armado,</hi> which no ſooner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued vs, but they retyred to a place where they had ſtreame and winde to their aduantage, and made themſelues faſt with foure cables before and behinde, and with a cable that reached from the one ſhippe to the other, and laye in ſuch manner that wee could not come neere vnto them, vnleſſe wee would winde our ſelues on boord of them in the night, I ſent diuerſe ſhippes vnto them, but could doe nothing. Then wee prepared a fire ſhip, thinking vnder the ſhotte of our Cannon to gette neere them, but it would not bee: they had placed all their Canon on the one ſide, and in the midſt all along their ſhippes they had layd Trees and Pipes filde vp with ſand, and had in-ſconſed them-ſelues in ſuch manner, that they could turne and winde their ſhippes as they would, and diſcharge their Cannon at their pleaſures, hauing a Northerlie winde that blew ſtrongly out of the valleys, ſo that wee ſought to get neere vnto them.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20675:11"/>
            <p>When wee came towards the point of the land, it was there calme vnder the high land, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming neere vnto them, the winde blew out of the Valleys, ſo that if wee would boord them, wee could not, vnleſſe we would burne our ſelues with them, which they deſire, (as it appeareth by the letters of the Vice-roy) for they make their rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning that they haue wone victory enough if by burning of two of their ſhippes, they burne one of ours: for the King cares not for his ſhippes, ſo he may thereby finde the meanes to hinder the Hollanders from their Nauigation.</p>
            <p>It was not good for vs to ſtay there any longer, for euery day wee loſt our anchors, ſo that our reſolution was to go to <hi>Pulo Lankeui,</hi> where they muſt of force ſtay, if they would goe for <hi>Mallacca,</hi> that ſo we might ſet vpon them in the maine Sea. The twentith day lying vnder <hi>Lankeui,</hi> ſixe miles from <hi>Poulo Bouton,</hi> wee determined to ſend the white Lyon to <hi>Queda</hi> to ſee if ſhe might get three or four hundred bales of Pepper there, becauſe at <hi>Dachin</hi> ſhee ſhould finde lading enough to ſerue her turne: But they could get nothing in <hi>Queda:</hi> For when they begin to gather the new Pepper, the old is gone, which is worth foure and twenty ryalls in <hi>Coſgie,</hi> and in <hi>Ihor,</hi> and ſo went to the reſt of our ſhips againe, lying vnder <hi>Pulo Lankeui</hi> to watch for the Portingales.</p>
            <p>The nine and twentith day the King of <hi>Queda</hi> (after that I burnt the Portugales ſhippes in his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20675:11"/>Riuer) cauſed twenty Portugales to bee kild, thinking ſo to doe mee a great pleaſure therein, becauſe I had ſent him word that hee ſhould ſhew ſome ſignes by his actions, that I might conceiue him to be my good friend. Your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes may iudge hereby what affection hee beareth vnto the Portugales: From thence there is nothing to bee brought away but Pepper and victuals, whereby thoſe of <hi>Mallacca</hi> are ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: this people alwaies hold with the ſtronger part. In the deliuering of the Portingale priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vnto the Vice roy before <hi>Mallacca,</hi> I had like to haue bene betrayed, for whereas I was ſo liberal that I gaue a hundred and ſeauenty Portingales, and as many Moores, for fiue or ſixe of my men which they had (but I reſerued the Captaines and three or foure more for to get the three thouſand ducats afore-ſaid) I ſent a note by a Portingale on ſhoare, to will the Vice-roy to ſend mee my men, and I would ſend him all his ſoldiers hole and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed, which if hee refuſed and held mee in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, I ſaid I would caſt all the Portingales ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord, he returned with a note, whereby the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy willed me to ſend him the Portingales, &amp; ſent me a bill of all their names both ſoldiers &amp; Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines &amp; all others that were in my hands, &amp; when my meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſhewed me that the priſoners were in danger of their liues; <hi>Andrew Hurtado</hi> made anſwer let him kill them, the reſt will fight better an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I vnderſtood, I returned the meſſenger preſently againe with this anſwer that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20675:12"/>if in the morning before Sunne riſing hee did not ſend mee all my Duch men I would kill all the Portingales; for I perceiued that the Viceroy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid mee off; hee returning brought with him three Duch-men, for there were no more in the towne, the reſt were in the <hi>Armado</hi> at <hi>Poulo Bouton:</hi> which hee promiſed to ſend, meane time I had call'd a Councell togither, and my white flagge hung out, and certainly if hee had ſtaid but two houres longer, theſe hundred and ſeauenty Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingales had beene caſt ouer-boord, for a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto them, not to mocke with vs another time, for when they haue their deſires, they ſcoffe at vs, and eſteeme vs to bee men that know not the courſe of the world, and that dare not (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the reuerence wee beare vnto them) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them any-way, and thus the boaſt before the <hi>Indian</hi> Princes.</p>
            <p>I thought to haue ſent a letter to the Viceroy, but deferr'd it for certaine cauſes, vntill ſome fitter time, to let him vnderſtand that wee intended to make warre-like ſoldiers, and that if hee would deale hardlyer with my men that hee ſhould take, then I had hether to done with his, hee would find himſelfe greatly deceiued, and that if he thought to ſtoppe my mouth with the Inquiſition and ſuch like maſquerados, and ſo keepe and conſume my men in his country, ſaying that hee could doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt th'Inquiſition, I and thoſe that ſhal come after mee to the <hi>Indies,</hi> would make warre
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20675:12"/>againſt th'Inquiſition, and caſt all their ſhaueling Fryers ouer-boord, which would concerne the Inquiſition and not him. May it therefore pleaſe the States to take ſuch order that theſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes may no longer terrifie vs with their viz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards: And thus much I cauſed to bee ſayd vnto the Viceroy him-ſelfe by the Captaines that were priſoners.</p>
            <p>Meane time I ſent a <hi>Praw</hi> from <hi>Queda</hi> to <hi>Pulo Lankeui</hi> with one of my men in it, to ſee whether the enemie lay ſtill at <hi>Poulo-bouton,</hi> who returned anſwer the nine and twentith day, that they were yet there, and brought two boyes priſoners with him, that tolde mee that they had ſent a <hi>Galliot</hi> to <hi>Mallacca</hi> to haue aduiſe from the <hi>Viceroy,</hi> to know what they ſhould do, whither they ſhold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the <hi>Indies</hi> or to <hi>Mallacca,</hi> for they durſt not leaue their aduantage, without command: they ſaid alſo, that when I thought to haue ſet on them with the fire-ſhippe and ſhotte vppon them, that twenty men were kild in the Admirall, ſeauen in <hi>Iohn Pintos</hi> ſhippe, and eight in <hi>Iacomo de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raris</hi> his couſins ſhippe wherein they went, but what was done in the other ſhippes they knew not.</p>
            <p>I perceiuing that there was no lading at <hi>Queda,</hi> and that the enemy would not leaue his place of aduantage, and that my time drew neere to go to the <hi>Molucques,</hi> durſt not ſtay any longer, for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20675:13"/>
               <hi>Amboine</hi> was of force to be fortified, whilſt <hi>Ternate</hi> was taken in by thoſe of <hi>Manilles,</hi> where the Gouernor <hi>Don Pedro de Souſa</hi> with a thouſand two hundred <hi>Spaniards</hi> and eight hundred <hi>Indians</hi> was come, and had taken the King priſoner.</p>
            <p>Therefore wee concluded, that the <hi>Vice-admirall</hi> with the <hi>White Lyon,</hi> and the great <hi>Sunne,</hi> ſhould goe for <hi>Achin,</hi> to ſee if they by any meanes could make the like agreement with the King, as wee had made with the King of <hi>Ihor,</hi> and to giue the <hi>White Lion</hi> her full lading, and ſo ſend her home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as alſo for to take in his owne lading if hee might, if not to goe preſently for <hi>Bantam,</hi> and there to take in their lading, and ſo to returne home-ward, if hee could bee ready againſt the laſt of February, or the middle of March at the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt, and to ſend the great <hi>Sunne</hi> to the coaſtes of <hi>Cormandel,</hi> but firſt to ſaile by <hi>Puncto de Galli</hi> vnder <hi>Celon,</hi> and there to trafficke and ſtay vntill the laſt of February, looking for the ſhippes of <hi>Bengale,</hi> and other places, which at that very time came from <hi>Couchien,</hi> and then were to goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Maſolipatan,</hi> hoping that they ſhall finde trafficke enough for <hi>Pauwels van Sold,</hi> beeing in the Shippe called <hi>Delfte,</hi> hath (as I vnderſtood of the <hi>Portugales</hi> that were taken before <hi>Queda</hi>) gotten three hundred bales of Cotten, linnen pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and alſo ſome Pintados.</p>
            <p>I intended to goe the inner waye to <hi>Bantam</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20675:13"/>with ſixe Ships, to ſee if I can make agreement al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with the King, and from thence to take our voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age towards <hi>Amboyna</hi> and the <hi>Molucques,</hi> for <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna</hi> muſt neceſſarily bee fortified, and wee muſt trie once againe to get the <hi>Molucques.</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Banda</hi> play the beaſts: ſome reſolution or other muſt bee taken, for our men with their goods, that are there not aſſured of their liues, and the goods of the company are much endangered. From thence we will make towards <hi>China,</hi> and trye what we can doe there.</p>
            <p>In the boate which I tooke before <hi>Malacca</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the three and twentith of October, I had ſeuen and thirtie bales, moſt part linnen cloath, and ſome <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lether, whereof ſeauen I ſent by the ſame boate to <hi>Amboyna,</hi> with foure thouſand ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, foure and forty men, and forty <hi>Negros,</hi> and the halfe part of his lading of Rice, that was ſpoyled: and to goe to <hi>Maraza</hi> to buy good Riſe, Fleſh, and ſome Pintados or Cotton, Painted cloath, for to carry to <hi>Amboina,</hi> and to tell them that I would follow after them in the end of December: The other ſeuenteene Bales I gaue to our Saylers for a prize, with a Bale of thred, to make them the more willinger and readier to fight, for that they had gotten but little bootie. I hope we ſhall finde lading at <hi>Amboina</hi> and <hi>Banda,</hi> for the Pintados or Cotton cloath of <hi>Panwels van Sold,</hi> ſhall no doubt haue prepared ſome-thing for vs.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20675:14"/>
            <p>I perceiue full well that wee ſhall haue long worke to doe about the <hi>Molucques,</hi> and that the time will fall out too ſhort for vs to goe to <hi>Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in <hi>China;</hi> but time will teach vs what is to bee done: if wee aſſure not <hi>Amboina,</hi> all our labour is in vaine, it is alſo againſt my opinion that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſhould come thether.</p>
            <p>The Generall <hi>Don Pedro de Souſa</hi> is made Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Ternate:</hi> The King that is taken is carryed to the Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> but his ſonne is leaft with the King of <hi>Sidor,</hi> I was in good hope to haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſome-thing, but my armie is too much weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and I finde what hurt I receiued from the ſhip that was burning before <hi>Malacca,</hi> for there I loſt the beſt men in my ſhippes: it is a ſtrange thing that they are ſo raſhlye and rudely giuen to the ſpoile, yet notwithſtanding I muſt bee content and holde my peace.</p>
            <p>Your worſhips may hereby perceiue, how wee haue behaued our ſelues theſe nine moneths here in the Straights, ſome-time fortunately, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time croſſely, but alwayes haue done the beſt we could, following your worſhips councell. I neuer wanted will nor courage to doe any ſeruice for my countrie, and though I haue not done as I would or deſired, yet I haue performed what I could, as it is manifeſt by the premiſes. I comfort my ſelfe with this ſaying: That it is enough in great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to will well, the Tree falls not at the firſt blow:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20675:14"/>if I could haue ouer-throwne thoſe ſeauen ſhippes that lay ſtill at <hi>Paulo Bouton,</hi> our time had beene well ſpent, but wee thought it not expedient to ſpendall our powder and munition. Wee haue yet a long iourney to make, wee muſt not bee too prodigall: I haue written my whole minde to the generall companie, what meanes there are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne warre againe.</p>
            <p>The Almightie GOD giue vs a proſperous voyage, that all our endeuours may tend to the good of our natiue countrey, and of the worſhipfull company.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>The</hi> 6. <hi>of Ianuary</hi> 1607.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
